Hello.  Today we'll look at an open
source alternative to the CI and CLD code.
Open CD, which is a completely open
code writing agent that works with
any model, from the same
subscription code, CD via API, as well as
any open source,
local models.  Today, we'll
look at how it differs, how to
set it up correctly, how to work with
local models, how to work with APIs,
and how to work with subscriptions so you can get
the most out of this
tool and make your code easier to write.
By the way, if you want to work more effectively
with code writing agents, we
recently released a course on code basics,
and you can also pre-register for a more
advanced course.  Links to this and that
course, as usual, are in the description.  So,
let's start with the question: why do we need
Open CD at all?  Essentially, OpenC is a completely
open source development tool
, which, unlike, for example,
Codeclo Gem, where you can't
see what's inside, here everything is
transparent.  You can install it on
any operating system and
use it with virtually any model.
Therefore, one of the advantages is
openness, working with any model without
additional hacks, as is
required, for example, to work
with Clotло and other models.
All of this essentially works out of
the box.  Moreover, it supports
watch and prom subscription.  That means if you
use a subscription code, it
will work here too.  Claude.  No, there's
even a separate story connected to this, when
Claude, in principle, began to put pressure on
various tools that
use code under the hood, such as,
for example, Open Clow, which, like Open
Code,  As a result, unfortunately,
the models can
only be used via the API, which is
fine if, for example,
you don't have a Claude subscription or your
subscription is banned, especially given the
recent bans that have hit
Code-Code.  Therefore, in this case, this
open source fully supports any
models.  And the big advantage is
that under the hood there is also
added support for LSP servers.  This is a
language-saving protocol that
allows you to
immediately catch any errors
you've written or
imported while you're still writing code, and LSP
immediately prompts you, which, by the way, doesn't
work everywhere.  For example, in the code-code there is
support for some LSPs, but
not all.  Here it is a full-fledged
LSP.  This is very cool.  Also multi-session
so you can run multiple
agents in parallel for work and
the ability to share your session for
debugging.  Overall, the functionality is quite
interesting.  Let's install it now and
take a look at it.  So, let's
install.  I'll be installing on a
Mac, so I'll be using Home Brew
to get everything
installed as quickly as possible.  If you have Windows or
Linux, you can use either npm or
b to install it, or both.  So,
let's go to the terminal and install.
At the same time, Home Brew has fairly
similar updates if
the version has been updated.  Well, a similar NBM
ban, if you install it, you can
run it.  When installing, I would like to
note the ban and NBM.  It is installed,
of course, globally so that you
can use it, but in the
overall installation, there is
essentially no difference between one way and the other.  After I
complete the installation, let's look at the
Opencode interface itself and what's inside.  So,
let's go over the basics of working with
OpenCD.  After launching,
our request UI opens.  By the way, I would like to point out the
benefits of Opencode.  Indeed, the
Terminal UI here is done better than
Claude's or Codex's.  It really
feels like a Terminal UI, not
just a command line where we
type things.  We have two modes for work,
just like the codex and the claude.
We change them using Tab.  Build, where we immediately
say that we need to build, and plan.  At the same time,
as we can see, we already have a
completely free model connected at the entrance.
In order to open the available
commands, we can press Ctrl P, and
our commands will open.  This is Switch
model to change the model.
As we can see, we now have
free Big Pckle Deeps QV4 Flash and
Nimatron 3 Superfree available.  You can also
connect your provider here.  Open CD, of course
, sells additional tokens and
subscriptions through the OpenCE Zen plan, where we
simply pay for certain models, and
OpenCD GO, a $10 subscription that
also includes a certain number of models.
You can also connect Open AI if
you have a Plus Pro subscription, or
connect IPK, GitHub Copilot,
Antropic, here only the API remains.  Well,
and, accordingly, Google.  In addition,
if we want to add some more
providers, then, in principle, we
can do this additionally through the
configuration.  Next up are the plugins.
Plugins are what allow you
to extend the functionality of your code.
Almost all of them are active by default, except for the ones that
give quick
hints on the key.  You can also
view commands using slsh.  If I
enter stress, then here we will see,
accordingly, agents.  We will see
divitor.  We'll
see all of this now.  The output connected to the MCP,
for example, which is now
automatically connected on the main Pcel case,
because I use it with the cloud and the
code, and it will be here too.  And in
principle, these commands can be similarly
found using Ctrl P.  Same thing mp.
You can change the agent
model accordingly, open div here, look at the
current skills that we
have, customize Open Code,
browser, and so on.  Well, these skills will be
installed later.  And of course,
we can change the theme if we want
our UI to be different in some way.  Overall,
everything is quite intuitive.  It is
very similar to what we usually see.
If we need a file, we
can, for example, do it
via a dog, specify a reference for some
image, and again, if it is already
scheduled, switch to the Monday mode.
We make plans accordingly.
We need to create a new chat, please
make new.  In principle, the basic
interactions are very similar to what we
saw with Uko, or more precisely, Claude and Codex.  But
let's now dive a little deeper.
Let's start with skills.  Skills in Open Code are
fully compatible with skills in ClD,
which is a huge advantage, including even
their syntax.  That's why when I
open Skills, I immediately have
access to a set of skills that are
globally installed for the cloud.
Moreover, skills are essentially separate
abilities that consist of a name and a
title.  This is what is basically
transmitted at startup.  And the skill itself will be
considered only when
it needs to be used.  It will be
either manually, if we want, for example,
to open a browser or something, or during
testing, for example, it can
use a browser to
open a site and check that everything
works or does not work.  Just like
Claude, this optimizes our
token usage.  That is, we see only
the title and description of the skill, and when
we apply it, it is read in full.  In
order to install a new skill, we
will need, for example, the same
SH skill, which allows you to add
skills.  For example, we can take
something like UIUX Pro Max.  We take it and
install it.  And after we
agree, in this folder, now
it will ask why to install it.  Not for
cldko, but for Open CD.  But in fact there is
no open source code here, so we put the
code for Cloud.  There are few options.  Within the framework of
the project, well, you can copy everything that is
here.  We are installing.  And now, when I
open Open CD and open Skills, I'll have
access to the new Skill UI UX Pro
Max, which analyzes our
current UI, tells me where we have errors,
where we made it incorrectly accessible,
and so on.  This is a big advantage.
Therefore, here you can
safely use any skills that are
available for SD or that you
have prepared for it together with OpenC.
Now let's do a simple task
using Open CD and look at inserting
images.  Overall, it works
similarly.  We can take,
for example, we have a bug like this right now.  I need to
copy the image, which we
now always do the same
style for creating a character.  Therefore,
using Ctrl V or Command V we
insert, respectively, one image.  And
then we can describe what actually
happens.  I will describe it again using my
voice for convenience.  Now, when
creating a character from a photograph, they are
assigned the same type.
He probably needs to vary it.
Application section.  Add everything here.
I'll make it vocal.  input.  And now
I switch to planning mode via Shift T
so that it
plans the changes.  Now we actually
have the
UI of our session.  On the right side you can
see MCP, LSP, current context,
how much money we spent, and the
percentage of contexts used.
Headline.  As we can see, we've already
spent just 18,000 tokens at the start.  This is
standard for agents.  They always
contain quite a lot of system
instructions.  On the left we see
the model and mode.  We are currently in
planning mode for GPT 5.5.  Again, it is
possible to enter something else here while
we watch.  And at the bottom the
context and Ctrl P of the current command are also displayed.  What
can we do with this session?
Accordingly, the parameters of the
MCP, skills and everything else
can be configured on the main one.  Now
we are analyzing the archetype and niche, which are
duplicated in the screenshot.  We can
work with them again, continue and write the
next query.  At the same time,
working with sessions is very convenient.  To do
this, we can press Ctrl P. And then
we have switch session.  And as we can see, we have
one session open today.  Next
we can create a second session.  And while the
first session is running, we can easily
move to the second session and
do something else.  In fact, from a
single Kernal UI we have the ability to
quickly switch between sessions and
see what's going on.  And this is
extremely convenient.  So, we have a plan.
Now it is necessary to implement this plan.
Switch to the build mode via the tab in
order to build.  and we say: "Okay,
make this change. Set the task."
Now it switches to build mode,
where it will be directly
implemented.  If we have tasks within the framework of one
of the tudus, as here, I specifically asked to
set tasks, on the right we see the
appearing tudus.  As we can see, it has
already been done, this is the bioson save point
, and he begins to throw in the
following tasks.  Essentially, these are the same
tudus that the clone has.  Here they are
displayed more, I think,
nicely, because on the right, you
can see, uh, what's happening.  Here
he has a list of tasks that he must
complete.  If I don't need it, I can
hide it by clicking, but here I see add
deterministic output, connect
profile output, add update texts,
run, accordingly,
TypeSescript checking.  These are, in principle, all
the tasks that he will complete.
This is a big advantage.  We see
progress.  Also, when he
edits files, here we see the
conidering.  Now he is still thinking, while
all his readings are the same as everywhere else
, everything he does is reflected.
Glob for searching, for example, read for
reading some file.  And now he
will edit some file.  I will
be able to see what was
edited as a result.  Now we
will prepare a patch.  LSP, by the way, is
disabled for some reason.  He has LSP here,
which is strange, because theoretically
Typescript LSP could be
connected here.  Of course, he thinks for a very long time
, but now he will produce the result.
So, we see there is the first change.
Here we can immediately see what we
have added and what we have removed.  And one
of the benefits that, at least to
me, seems convenient is that I can
open a divure.
Defure will block me the changes that are
currently present in the project.  I can
go over them.  Well, we can remove everything
that concerns agents, leave here
only the clot agents, in short,
all these co-packages can be
left.  And we can see that what
has changed for us is what he just
adjusted.  Here I can see
the changes and see how it worked correctly
or incorrectly.  If I press M,
let's just go here.  I'll press M, which means
I'll mark it as review.  That is,
I can mark for myself those files that
I looked at, that he edited
correctly, because in any case we
need to move on.  Using the tab I can
move between these two cells.
Accordingly, I tab here, tab
here.  N switches to the next file,
but in this case, for example, Agent MD.
He initialized it himself.
By the way, you can manually initialize it via
sniit, or in this case it
initialized it itself.  If
I want the previous file, then I
need to view the file.  If I do
n't like something, I can
comment further on what will actually
be there.  Here you can also use
source 3 or last turn, that is,
what we changed in the
last iteration, and not the entire tree.
If I switch, I'll only see the
changed files within that iteration,
which is often more convenient than looking at work 3,
which will contain changes to,
for example, cloud files that I
don't need right now.  We see that he
changed, accordingly, the
interface file, the service, or rather, the spec, he
changed, actually, the file of the
inference service and
adjusted the orchestrator.
Accordingly, here we now have
all the changes.  By the time we return to
the list, we will see, firstly,
that it is almost finished, and immediately on the right are
modified files.  These are, in fact, the files
that we saw in the diff.  That is,
here we can immediately review the code based on
how it was corrected.  In
most other Calis you still
usually need to open a separate
editor to see what was
done and how well it was done
.  Now let's look at how we
can manage our session and
conduct a
review of the year's results.  First, we
looked at manual review.  Secondly, as
in most cases, there is a
team that
reviews the changes that we
currently have.  You can ask
him to delete Commit, Branch, if you have
GitHub connected, MCP, or even PR.
Also, if we press Ctrl P,
we have a few more options here.  This is
jump to message, when we can
move to a specific message and
see what happened there.   It's
extremely convenient for quick navigation in the console
, because without it you have to
scroll a lot.  And one of the good things
is fork conversation.  Fork allows
us to roll back to certain
discussions and then create a new
session that will contain only the changes up to
that discussion.  And it turns out that in a
new session we can, from some point on,
continue doing something else.
For example, if we don’t like what
happened there afterwards, we move on and
continue our discussion.  Thanks to
this, we can very easily get a
high-quality adjustment of what
we have.  Launches revw again.  And
here there is also an opportunity to make
our conversions compact.
Our context is starting to fill in.  More than 50% of
the context can usually lead to
hallucinations, so it’s better to make a
compact.  In addition, if you don’t
like the previous message and want to
remove it, there is a quick command,
respectively, Ctrl Xu or
Ctrlp PV message in order to
cancel the previous message.  Well, and,
accordingly, the rest of the settings
are mostly UI settings,
when we want to hide Tool Details,
hide HB or something like that.  Well,
now let's see how we can
use it not necessarily with a
codex subscription, but, for example, just with
some free model that
you can run locally.  Now,
how to use OpenCD with local
models?  You can use
either OLAM or LM Studio to run local models
.  At your discretion, we will
use OLAM.  Copy the model.  I
will be using the updated KN 35
9B model, which only takes up 6
gigs of RAM, because otherwise the
laptop will not have enough space for anything
else.  Let's launch.  Since
I already have the model downloaded, it simply suggests
modifying the Open Code Model now.  And
click yes.  What will happen?  will be
launched as the model is loaded into memory.  And
then we now have the model itself, actually
.  If we open the Ctrl P
mode, we will now see not only GPT
5.5, which we did not have, but also Quen 3.5
based on Olaama.  Let's ask him hello
and see how fast he gets tokens.   Let me
say right away that this is still a
local model, on which I have a
bunch of applications running, screen recording is in progress
, and at the same time, the performance of the
local model will most likely not be the
most optimal.  just a word of
greeting.  He must now first
load it into memory and then
begin to respond.  Let's see how many
tokens it produces per second, but I do
n't think it's super productive.  If
you have a high-performance computer,
for example, you have a
separate video card, you have 3264 GB of
RAM, then, in principle, you can
try downloading a more
advanced model than just the Quen 3.5.
3.6 has just come out.  She requires a little
more space in her place.  I
can't run it, but you
can, of course.  As we can see, it still takes a
long time to warm up.  And all this
time, while I was telling this story, we still don’t have an
answer.  That is, if you are
still counting on local
models, then it is worth keeping in mind that you
need really good hardware for
local models to produce anything
intelligible.  And, of course, it
won’t be comparable to GPT 5.5, or
Opus, or anything else.  Well, if
you don't have a powerful computer like me, then the
easiest thing is to use our
custom provider, which allows you
to connect all cloud models to clclod or
even Open Code.  What is needed for
OpenCD to work properly with a
custom provider?  You need to
modify the configuration manually.  S
is true not only for our
connection there.  You can take
any other provider that
provides API access, which is what
we actually do, and take a
token and a custom URL.  In this case,
I will show you the token and change it later
.  Next we need to go to
config open jondify.
For this purpose we add a new
section here: provider.  We indicate the
purple school provider.  Accordingly, npm is a
deck, so DK is the name of the base URL
that is displayed in your account from
V1.  The only thing is that at the end,
because without V1 he will swear that this is not the
way.  Therefore, we need to
add V1 here.  key and further
models.  We have the following models available: Opus Sonet
or Hku.  After that, save and
open Open Code.  Now in the
model menu you will have access
not only to the latest
models, but also to Purple School, Clod,
Opus, Sonet, and Haiku models.  Well, for example,
let's choose Haiku and write to him:
"Hello."  Now, instead of
spinning the fan on my poor old
MacBook, we'll get the answer from the cloud.
And here he will answer everything we
need.  As we can see, he
certainly eats up a lot of tokens, but again, these are
system tokens that are sent with
code about who he is and what he
does.  Accordingly, the answer is now
obtained from modelX.  And I can change
there for a more advanced model.  This
works with any cost-effective provider
you want to connect to Open
CD.  Well, I hope this was
helpful to you.  If so, don't forget to
like and subscribe.  Tell us in
the comments what you use:
Codex, Claude, or OpenCode?  And we
will see each other in a week.